Finding Aid for Erich A. Walter papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Erich A. Walter papers 1887-1976 1930s-1940s
Walter, Erich A., (Erich Albert), 1897-1977.
2014006 Aa 2
Erich A. Walter (1897-1977) was a faculty member at the University of Michigan for 53 years, beginning as an instructor in rhetoric in 1919 and ending as the Assistant to the President (Harlan Hatcher) and the Secretary of the University. In addition to his work at the University, Walter was a very successful editor and author, his most popular works being the Essay Annual (1933-1941) and A Pictorial History of the Great Lakes, which he co-authored with Harlan Hatcher. This collection contains Walter's University related papers, including correspondence, research and projects, essays and speeches, and photographs used in and drafts of A Pictorial History of the Great Lakes, in addition to papers related to his work as an editor on Essay Annual and Toward Today.
3.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by the Estate of Marie Walter Goodhew (donor no. 10831 )in September of 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Erich A. Walter was born in Zanesville, Ohio on July 5, 1897. Despite his early roots in Ohio, Walter was a graduate of the Ann Arbor High School class of 1915. After his graduation, Walter received a Bachelor of Arts degree from the University of Michigan's Literary College in 1919 and immediately joined the faculty as an instructor in rhetoric. He earned his Master of Arts degree in 1921, also from the University of Michigan. Shortly after, in 1922, Walter married Meta Henne, a 1919 graduate of the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts at the University of Michigan, with whom he had three children. Furthermore, he studied at the British Museum, London, England, for a time in 1930 and 1931 and in 1937 and 1938. In 1955, Walter served as the University's delegate to the Installation of H. M. Queen Elizabeth, the Queen Mother, as Chancellor of the University of London.
Walter's career at the University of Michigan was marked by a series of promotions throughout his 53 year relationship with the school. In 1923, Walter was promoted to assistant professor of English and was made chairman of the Freshman English Program in 1927. He was promoted to associate professor in 1935, while also taking on the new role of chairman of Academic Counselors. Then, in 1938 he was made Assistant Dean of the Literary College, and later Associate Dean in 1945. In 1947, Walter was given a full professorship at the university and was appointed Director of the Office of Student Affairs, a title which was changed to Dean of Students in 1948. He remained in this role until his appointment in 1953 as Assistant to the President, who at this time was President Harlan Hatcher. Five years later, in 1958, he was also appointed secretary of the Regents. Walter retired from the University in 1967, at the age of 70, upon which he was appointed Assistant Emeritus to the President, Secretary Emeritus of the University, and Professor Emeritus of English.
In addition to these roles, Walter was chairman of the Michigan Memorial-Phoenix Project in 1946 and 1947. He was a member of the Board of Trustees of the Ann Arbor Public Schools from 1933 to 1939, serving as president during his last year on the board. From 1946 to 1953, he was a member of the Board of Directors of Cranbrook School for Boys, Bloomfield Hills, Mich., filling the role of secretary in 1949. From 1949 to 1955, he was also a member of the Board of Directors of the Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce. Walter was a member of the Modern Language Association, National Council of Teachers of English, Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters, American Association of University Professors, English Speaking Union, Michigan College Association, Quadrangle Club, Phi Kappa Phi, Sigma Rho Tau, and was decorated Star of Italian Solidarity, Second Class, in 1962.
Walter served as the editor for numerous publications: University Readings (with C.D. Thorpe) in 1931; Bibliography of Contemporary Literature, 1932-1937 (English Journal); Essay Annual (yearly volumes), 1933-1941; Toward Today, 1938; and Religion and the State University 1958. He also co-authored A Pictorial History of the Great Lakes with Harlan Hatcher in 1963. Erich Walter died on April 1, 1977 in South Bend, Indiana, at the age of 79.
The Erich A. Walter papers collection contains Walter's University related papers, including correspondence, research and projects, essays and speeches, and photographs used in and drafts of A Pictorial History of the Great Lakes, as well as papers related to his work as an editor on Essay Annual and Toward Today.
Subjects:
Editors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Great Lakes (North America); Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Walter, Erich A., (Erich Albert), 1897-1977.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- University papers
  The University papers series (1.3 linear feet, 1887-1976) contains various items related to Walter's time at the University of Michigan. Included in this series are: photographs and negatives of the pictures used in Walter and Hatcher's A Pictorial History of the Great Lakes, along with items of research relating to the project and drafts of the project; research projects that Walter conducted while working at the University, including the Connecting Channels project, his research on bridge engineer D.B. Steinman, the Fr. Gagnieur research project, papers relating to the Phoenix Memorial project (in which there is a letter from Orson Welles to Walter regarding what the University should do in terms of a memorial), and his research for the Alexander Ruthven biography; general correspondence as well as his correspondence with Edmund G. Love; biographical papers regarding the University of Michigan; and Walter's speeches, essays, and other writings.
  - Connecting Channels project 1956-1960 (Box 1)
  - D.B. Steinman research 1955-1962 (Box 1)
  - Edmund G. Love correspondence 1954-1971 (Box 1)
  - Essays by Walter 1931-1946 with undated (Box 1)
  - Fr. Gagnieur research project 1928-1933 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - 1935-1937 (Box 1)
    - 1938-1941 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Interview transcript re. working with President Harlan Hatcher undated (Box 1)
  - Letters of recommendation 1936-1942 (Box 1)
  - Letters re. appointment as Dean of Students 1946 (Box 1)
  - Phoenix Memorial project 1947-1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
    (with gaps)
  - Pictorial History of the Great Lakes
    - Correspondence 1957-1966 (Box 1)
    - Draft undated (Box 1)
    - Images
      - Negatives undated, 1 envelopes; 1 folders (Box 1)
      - Photographs 1887-1958, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (scattered)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1959-1964 (Box 1)
  - Reports 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Sabbatical in England 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Ruthven biography 1962, 1970-1976 (Box 2)
  - Speeches undated with 1936 (Box 2)
  - To-day: A Scribbling Diary for 1933, 1932 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan biographical papers undated with 1956 (Box 2)
- Editorial papers
  The Editorial papers series (2.1 linear feet, 1933-1949) consists of the materials relating to two of Walter's editorial ventures, the Essay Annual volumes from 1933-1941, and Toward Today. There are two subseries within this series, one relating to Essay Annual and the other relating to Toward Today. The papers included are papers relating to the administrative duties of editorship (including correspondence with authors, of whom E.B. White, James Thurber, and John Steinbeck are among), biographical notices, essays included in the volumes, or, in Toward Today's case, excerpts from the volume, permissions, reports and reviews of the volumes, and letters of regret to authors whose writings were not used, and statements of sales.
  - Essay Annual
    - 1933
      - Administrative/background (Box 2)
      - Author correspondence (Box 2)
    - 1934
      - Author correspondence (Box 2)
    - 1935
      - Administrative/background, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Author correspondence (Box 2)
      - Biographical notices (Box 2)
      - Essays included (Box 2)
      - Reports and reviews (Box 2)
    - 1936
      - Administrative/background, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Author correspondence (Box 2)
      - Biographical notices (Box 2)
      - Essays included (Box 2)
      - Reports and reviews (Box 2)
    - 1937
      - Administrative/background, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Author correspondence (Box 2)
      - Biographical notices (Box 2)
      - Essays included (Box 3)
      - Reports and Reviews (Box 3)
    - 1938
      - Administrative/background, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Author correspondence (Box 3)
      - Biographical notices (Box 3)
      - Essays included (Box 3)
      - Reports and reviews and nominations for Essay Annual 1939 (Box 3)
    - 1939
      - Administrative/background, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Author correspondence, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Biographical notices (Box 3)
      - Essays included (Box 3)
      - Reports and reviews (Box 3)
    - 1940
      - Administrative/background (Box 3)
      - Author correspondence, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Biographical notices (Box 3)
      - Essays included (Box 3)
      - Letters of regret (Box 3)
    - 1941
      - Administrative/background, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Author correspondence (Box 4)
      - Biographical notices (Box 4)
      - Essays included (Box 4)
  - Toward Today
    - Administrative/Background 1938, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Author correspondence (Box 4)
    - Biographical notices 1938 (Box 4)
    - Excerpts 1938 (Box 4)
Related Collections
Outside of this collection, Erich Walter has a photograph collection and a sound recordings collection, both located at the Bentley Historical Library, that are unrelated but possibly of interest. This collection is of value to those interested on the history of the University of Michigan, the history of the Great Lakes region, and those interested in an in-depth look into editorial work, especially when dealing with authors, and dealing with the ins-and-outs of copyright and publishing. The collection is divided into two series: the University papers series and the Editorial papers series.